Register of the Eugene Frederick Quinn papers, 1822-2005
Hoover Institution Archives
Eugene Frederick Quinn papers
1822-2005
1960-1970
72099
Hoover Institution Archives
18 manuscript boxes, 3 microfilm reels, 2 envelopes, 1 expanding folder, 4 sound tape reels (7.6 linear feet)
Research notes and drafts, lists, writings, interviews, copies of government documents, printed matter, tapes of tribal chants, memorabilia, and photographs relating to the Beti society of Cameroon. Many of these documents were used by E. F. Quinn as research material for his dissertation, entitled "Changes in Beti Society, 1887-1960" (University of California, Los Angeles, 1970). Entire collection also available on microfilm (7 reels).
Quinn, Eugene Frederick
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1972.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Collection is also available on microfilm (7 reels).
Biographical Note
1935 September 16 Born, Oil City, Pennsylvania
1957 AB, Allegheny College
1958-1959 Information officer, U.S. Information Agency, American Embassy, Rabat, Morocco
1959-1961 Cultural affairs officer, U.S. Information Agency, Port-au-Prince, Haiti,
1961-1963 Country public affairs officer, U.S. Information Agency, Ouagadougou, Upper Volta
1964-1966 Field representative, U.S. Information Agency, Joint United States Affairs Office, Saigon, Vietnam
1966 MA, African Studies, University of California, Los Angeles
1966-1968 Country public affairs officer, U.S. Information Agency, American Embassy, Yaounde, Cameroon
1969 MA, Modern European History, University of California, Los Angeles
1969-1970 Deputy Examiner, Board of Examiners of the Foreign Service, Washington, D.C. Chairman, State Department Task Force Working Group on Recruitment, Examination and Employment
1970 Author, "Changes in Beti Society, 1887-1960" [PhD dissertation] PhD, History, University of California, Los Angeles
1974 Diploma, Theological Studies, Virginia Theological Seminary
1975 Ordained to ministry, Episcopal Church
1975-1978 Counselor, Embassy for Press and Cultural Affairs, Prague, Czechoslovakia
1981 Appointed career member with class of counselor, Senior Foreign Service
1981-1983 Director, foreign service personnel, Voice of America, Washington, D.C.
1983-1985 Deputy assistant secretary, public affairs, Department of Transportation
1985-1986 Director, Office of Public Affairs, Voice of America
1986 Appointed career member with class of minister-counselor, Senior Foreign Service
1986-1991 International coordinator for the Bicentennial of the United States Constitution, Director's Office, United States Information Agency
1992- Consultant, international affairs
1993 Author, The Federalist Papers Reader
1993-1995 Director, Rule of Law programs, Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe, Office of Democratic Institutions and Human Rights, Warsaw
1994 Author, To Heal the Earth: A Theology of Ecology
1998 Author, Democracy at Dawn: Notes from Poland and Points East
1999 Author, Human Rights and You: A Guide for the States of the Former Soviet Union and Central Europe
2000 Author, The French Overseas Empire
2001 Author, To Be A Pilgrim: The Anglican Ethos in History
2002 Author, African Saints: Saints, Martyrs, and Holy People from the Continent of Africa
2002 Author, The Courthouse at Indian Creek: The First Five Years of the Greenbelt Maryland Federal Courthouse
2003 Co-author, Pride, Faith, and Fear: Islam in Sub-Saharan Africa
2004 Author, Building the "Goodly Fellowship of Faith": A History of the Episcopal Church in Utah, 1867-1996
2006 Author, In Search of Salt: Changes in Beti (Cameroon) Society, 1880-1960
2008 Author, The Sum of All Heresies: The Image of Islam in Western Thought
2012 Author, Welcoming the Interfaith Future: Religious Pluralism in a Global Age
Scope and Contents of Collection
Research notes and drafts, lists, writings, interviews, copies of government documents, printed matter, tapes of tribal chants, memorabilia, and photographs relating to the Beti society of Cameroon. Many of these documents were used by E. F. Quinn as research material for his dissertation, entitled "Changes in Beti Society, 1887-1960" (University of California, Los Angeles, 1970).
Africa.; Beti (Bantu tribe); Cameroon--History.; Cameroon--Social life and customs.; Cameroon.; Ethnology--Cameroon.
- PROJECT FILE FOR BETI SOCIETY STUDY, 1966-1974 (Boxes 1-2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, drafts, research notes, outlines, resumes, and bibliographies related to Frederick Quinn's project to write a history of Beti society in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries. The history is an unpublished dissertation, entitled "Changes in Beti Society, 1887-1960" (University of California, Los Angeles, 1970). See box 17 for a bound copy of the dissertation.
  - Project correspondence (Box 1)
    - General
    - Tsala, Abbe Theodore, 1968-1971
    - Zoa, Jean, Archbishop of Yaounde, Cameroun, 1967
  - Drafts (incomplete) of "Beti Society in the Nineteenth Century," by Frederick Quinn
  - Notes
    - General
    - Notecards
    - Notebooks
  - Bibliographies
  - Resumes
  - Outlines, chronological and topical (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
- CHRONOLOGICAL SERIES, 1822-1961 (Boxes 3-9)
  Photoprints, photocopies, and typewritten transcripts of documents in the British Public Record Office, the Cameroun National Archives, and the Institut de Recherches scientifiques du Cameroun, and photoprints and photocopies of selected pages of French and German publications, collected by Quinn during the 1960s, arranged chronologically by date of document or publication, with undated documents contained in the folders marked undated. A partial list of documents and publications contained in the 1916-1950 folders, prepared by Quinn, is contained in the first folder.
  See also: Declassified U.S. Government Records, 2016 January release of records.
  - List (partial) of documents in 1916-1950 folders (Box 3)
  - 1822
  - 1827-1828
  - 1829-1830
  - 1832-1833
  - 1885
  - 1889-1890
  - 1892(?)
  - 1894-1900
  - 1901 (Box 4)
  - 1903-1908
  - 1909-1919 (Box 5)
  - 1902-1921(?)
  - 1922-1923
  - 1924-1933 (Box 6)
  - 1933
    Chef de Region Cournaire. "Note sur les coutumes des populations de la region du Nyong et Sanaga," typewritten transcript.
  - 1934-1945 (Box 7)
  - 1946-1951 (Box 8)
  - 1952-1961 (Box 9)
  - Undated
    - General
    - Dugast. "Documents recueillis en pays Mangisa (Documents collected in the Land of the Mangisa)"
      Photoprint of typescript.
    - Sheikh al-Islam (Six Months Ago)
      Photocopy of untitled manuscript in North African Arabic with English translation attached.
    - Talinde. "Quelques fétiches des Ewondo (Fetishes of the Ewondo)"
- COLLECTED UNPUBLISHED WRITINGS, 1903-1968 (Boxes 10-12)
  Holographs, typescripts, transcripts, photoprints, photocopies, and carbon copies of unpublished writings in English, French, and Ewondo, for the most part prepared or collected in response to inquiries made by Quinn among the inhabitants of the Yaounde Region of the Cameroun, arranged alphabetically by author or title.
  - Atangana, Charles. "Discussion of the Evolution of the Role of Chief in the Yaounde Region of the Cameroun,", 1929, 1968 (Box 10)
    Typewritten transcript with photocopy and carbon copies in French, with an introductory note entitled, "Charles Atangana and the Ewondo Chiefs: A Document by Frederick Quinn."
  - Atangana Amengue, Henri
    - "Definitions of Forms of Sorcery among the Beti,", 1968
      Holograph and typescript in French.
    - "Le tam-tam ou 'Nkoul' (The Tom-Tom),", 1968
      Holograph and typescript with carbon copy in French.
  - Atangana, Abbe Tobie. "Nti Angono Woo (Zee) (The Leopard Named Zee),", circa 193?, 1968
    Typewritten transcript in Ewondo with French translation by Abbe Theodore Tsala.
  - "Benediction nuptiale de la jeune fille par ses parents (Nuptial Blessing of a Young Girl by Her Parents),", undated
    Typescript in Ewondo and French.
  - Betene (also: Beteyene and Beteyne), Abbe Pierre
    - "Le Chant dans la vie traditionnelle du Beti (Song in the Traditional Life of the Beti),", circa 1967-1968
      Typescript in French.
    - "D'une generation a une autre: etude des changements survenues dans notre societe depuis 25 ans (From One Generation to the Next: A Study of the Changes Occuring in Our Society Over the Past Twenty-Five Years),", 1968
    - "Enquete sur les Beti du Sud-Cameroun (An Investigation of Beti Society in the Southern Cameroun),", 1967
      Typescript in French and Ewondo.
  - Bikoa, Materne and Pierre Betene. "La Musique Traditionnelle en pays Beti (Traditional Music in the Land of the Beti),", 1967, undated
    Typescript with carbon copy and photocopy in French and Ewondo, with an introductory note by Frederick Quinn.
  - Bikoa, Materne. "An Investigation of the Evolution of Beti Society,", 1967
  - "Biographie de Charles Atangana Ntsama, Chef superieur des Ewondo (Biography of Charles Atangana Ntsama, Chief Superior of the Ewondo),", circa 1968
    Typescript with carbon copy in French.
  - "Chant (Les Ewondo pleurent Atangana Ntsama) (Chant: The Ewondo Weep for Atangana Ntsama),", undated
    Carbon copy of typescript in Ewondo and French.
  - Chilver, E. M. and P. M. Kaberry. Draft notes on "The Kingdom of Kom (West Cameroun) in the 19th Century,", 1964
    Photocopy of typescript.
  - "Les croyances des Beti a travers la semantique et les maximes (Religious Beliefs of the Beti as Revealed in Their Semantics and Maxims),", undated
    Carbon copy of typescript in French and Ewondo.
  - Ebogo, Abbe Apollinaire
    - "Les Beti (The Beti),", 1967
    - "Les Beti, supplement aux recherches sociologiques sur les 'Beti de Nnanga' (The Beti: Supplement to the Sociological Research on the Beti of Nnanga),", 1968
      Typescript in French with a letter, list of questions, and a list of project expenses attached.
    - "Remarques sur les 'Notes sur les coutumes des populations de la region du Nyong et Sanaga,' par Cournaire (Remarks on the 'Notes on the Customs of the People of the Nyong and Sanaga Region,' by Cournaire),", 1933 December
  - Embolo, Abbe Laurent. "Rapport a l'enquete sur les Betis (Report on the Inquiry about the Beti),", 1967
  - Essomba, Abbe Frederick. "Religion traditionnelle (Traditional Religion),", 1968
    Mimeograph in French.
  - "Le fétichisme et la guerison en pays Bassa (Fetishism and Herbal Medicine in the Land of the Bassa),", undated
  - Foudda, Max Abe. "Histoire des Betis (Ewondo) (History of the Ewondo Beti),", 1967
    Typescript with carbon copy in French and Ewondo.
  - "Genealogie de la tribu Mbid' Ambani (Genealogy of Mbid' Ambani Tribe),", 1968
  - "Genealogie generale de la tribu D'Enoa (Genealogy of the D'Enoa Tribe),", undated
  - "Genealogy of the Nda-Bod Mvog Amougui Mbezele, or Mvog Elomo,", undated
  - Laburthe-Tobra, Philippe. "Essai de synthese sur l'histoire des populations dites 'Beti' de la region de Minlaba (sud du Nyong) (Essay on the History of the Beti of the Minlaba Region [South of the Nyong]),", 1973
    Mimeograph of a communication in French.
  - "Le mariage des Beti et ses differentes sortes (The Variety of Marriages among the Beti),", undated
  - Mballa Foe, Martin. "Genealogie generale de la tribu Mvog Amougou (Genealogy of the Mvog Amougu Tribe),", 1968
    Typescript with carbon copy in French; notes of an interview with Owono Ndi Cyprien attached.
  - Mvondo, Marcel, II
    - "Une image de l'Afrique precoloniale (A Description of Pre-Colonial Africa),", 1968
      Carbon copy of typescript in French.
    - "De la poesie camerounaise (Camerounian Poetry),", 1968
    - "Le 'nken' (The Nken Bell),", undated
  - Onana, Ambroise Alfred Marzavan (Box 11)
    - "Genealogie des Beti (Genealogy of the Beti),", 1967
      Photoprint of holograph in Ewondo; holograph and carbon copy of typescript French translation by Onana.
    - "Genealogie generale de la tribu Mvog-Amugu (Genealogy of the Mvog-Amugu Tribe),", 1967-1968
      Typescript with carbon copy in Ewondo; holograph and typescript with carbon copy French translation by Onana.
    - "Minkana/Paraboles (Proverbs),", 1967-1968?
      Typescript with carbon copy in Ewondo and French, and partial holograph in Ewondo and French.
    - "Les rites fétichistes anciens des Ewondo (Fetish Rites of the Ewondo),", 1967-1968?
      Photoprint of holograph in Ewondo; holograph and typescript with carbon copy French translations by Onana.
  - "Open Letter to Pope John XXIII from the Diocesan Clergy of Yaounde, Cameroun,", 1960 October 6
    Carbon copy of typescript.
  - "Principaux instruments de musiques des Beti (Principal Musical Instruments of the Beti),", undated (Box 12)
  - "La procedure du mariage au sein de certaines familles cotieres du Cameroun - La dot (The Marriage Customs of Certain Coastal Families of the Cameroun - The Dowry),", undated
  - "Situation sociale de la femme chez les Beti (The Social Status of Women among the Beti),", undated
    Carbon copy of typescript (incomplete) in French and Ewondo.
  - The, M. S. de. "Influences des femmes sur l'evolution des structures sociales chez les Beti du Sud-Cameroun (The Influence of Women on the Evolution of the Social Structure of the Beti of the Southern Cameroun),", 1965 March
    Typewritten transcript with carbon copy of a thesis presented to the Ecole Pratique des Hautes Etudes, VIe Section, University of Paris.
  - Tjamag, Louis. "Le foot-ball au Cameroun (Soccer in the Cameroun),", 1968
  - Tsala, Abbe Theodore
    - "Benedictions et maledictions (Benedictions and Maledictions),", 1968
    - Description of Beti society, 1968
      Untitled typescript with carbon copy beginning "Geographie et Populations (Geography and People)...," in French and Ewondo.
    - "Charles Atangana Ntsama"
    - "Curriculum vitae de l'abbe Theodore Tsala Etono (Biography of Abbe Theodore Tsala Etono),", 1968
    - "Le gouvernement des Beti (The Government of the Beti),", 1968
    - "Interdits (Interdictions),", 1968
    - "Monseigneur Francois Xavier Vogt,", 1968
    - "La mort de Zibi Ngomo et les sacrifices humains (The Death of Zibi Ngomo and Human Sacrifices),", 1968
    - "Les noms des jours (The Names of Days),", 1968
    - "Organization Judiciaire (Organization of the Judiciary),", undated
    - "Les parents et les enfants: Bebonde ai bon (Parents and Children),", 1968
      Typescript with carbon copies in French and Ewondo.
    - "Principales valeurs sociales des Beti (Principal Social Values of the Beti),", 1968
    - "Regles de vie sacerdotale (Rules of Priestly Life),", 1968
      Typescript with carbon copies in French.
    - "Des vedettes de l'evangelisation du Cameroun (Prominent Figures in the Evangelizing of the Cameroun),", 1968
  - Vieter, P. "Erinnerungen aus Kamerun, 1890-1903 (Recollections of the Cameroun, 1890-1903),", circa 1903
    Photocopy of typewritten transcript in German.
  - Vincent, Jeanne-Francoise and Abbe Theodore Tsala. "Mort, revenants et sorciers d'apres les proverbes des Beti du Sud-Cameroun (Death, Ghosts, and Witches, Based on Proverbs of the Beti of the Southern Cameroun),", 1968
    Photocopy of typescript in French.
  - Wars among Beti Tribes, circa 1968
    Untitled typescript with carbon copy in French.
  - Miscellaneous
    Partial manuscripts in French and Ewondo.
- ORAL INTERVIEWS, 1967-1968 (Box 13)
  Handwritten and typewritten transcripts, notes, and correspondence related to oral interviews conducted, for the most part, among Beti tribal elders by Quinn, arranged alphabetically by name of interviewee.
  - Atangana, Francois. Near Mbalmayo, 1967 May 2 (Box 13)
  - Atangana Amengue, Henri. Mfou, 1968 April 5, 18, May 26
  - Ateba, Albert and Philibert, 1968 April 19
  - Betayene, Jean Faustin. Yaounde, 1968?
    "Conversation Concerning Colonial Occupation and the Independence Movement in Cameroun History."
  - Binzi, Benoit. Near Yaounde, 1968 May 14, 26
  - Bissome Dza, Paul (Bisso Mezda, Gotefried), 1968 March 18, 26
  - Brunchweg, Henri, 1968 June 1
    Notes on conversation.
  - Essomba, Abbe Frederick. Mbalmayo, 1968 March 14
  - Fonda, Max Abe. Mkolbewa, 1967 December 23, 1968 January 6
  - Mballa Foe, Martin and Owona Nde Cyprian. Mbalmayo, 1968 March 14-15
  - Mbida, Mr. and Mrs. Andre Marie., 1968 July 28
  - Mbida, Mbelle, 1968 February 15
  - Mebe, Pierre, 1967-1968
    April?, May 10, June 30, July 7, 12, 14, 20, 22, August 6, November 1, 8, 16, and December 21, 1967; February 8, 22, 1968.
  - Messie Alogo. Mfou, 1968 April 4, 12
  - Okah Mbana Fabian, Fouda Ngono Jean, Ayissi Nsimi Laurant, Ahanda Ayissi Etienne, and Alima Etoundi Charles. Ngondemezap, 1968 March 18
  - Onana Mbida, Hubert. Ngomedzap, 1968 March 19, August 5-7
  - Ondoua Awoumou, Laurent. Near Mbalmayo, 1968 March 14, 31
  - Owono, Joseph, 1968 July 8
  - Tsala, Abbe Theodore. Mvolye, 1968
    February 13, 15, 17, 22, 24, March? 2, 12, 19, 26, April 2, 7, 22, 24, May 1, 5, 14, 30, June 6, July 6, 10, 14, and August 1, 1968.
  - Ze, Daniel, 1968 April 13
  - Ze, Marie-Jean, 1968 April 4
  - Zoa, Archbishop Jean. Yaounde, 1967 November 30
- PUBLISHED MATTER, 1893-1970 (Boxes 13-16)
  Transcripts, photoprints, photocopies, offprints, resumes, and translations of periodical literature, books, and other printed matter in English, French, German, and Ewondo, collected by Quinn, in part from the London Library of the Royal Geographic Society, arranged alphabetically by author or title.
  - Alexandre, Pierre. "Proto-histoire du groupe beti-bulu-fang: essai de synthese provisoire (Proto-History of the Beti-Bulu-Fang Group: An Essay),", 1962-1963 (Box 13)
    Photocopy.
  - Atangana, Charles
    - "Aken So (le rite So) chez les Yaoundes-Banes (The 'So' Rite among the Yaoundes-Banes)," Anthropos, 1942
      Typewritten transcript in French and Ewondo.
    - "Lebenslauf Karl Atangana/Curriculum Vitae de Charles Atangana (Life of Charles Atangana)," selection from Heepe (ed.), Yaounde-Text, 1919
      Photocopy in German; typescript transcript in French.
  - "Avec Charles Atangana: Une page d'histoire camerounaise (With Charles Atangana: A Page from Camerounian History)," L'Effort Camerounais, 1958 May 10
  - Binet, Jacques
    - "Budgets familiaux des planteurs de cacao au Cameroun (Family Budgets of Cacao Planters in the Cameroun),", 1956
      In L'Homme d'outre-mer (The Man Over-Seas) series of the Conseil superieur de la Recherche sociologique outre-mer (Council on Over Seas Sociological Research). Photocopy.
    - "Groupes socio-professionnels au Cameroun (Socio-Professional Groups in the Cameroun)," Cahiers Internationaux de Sociologie, XXIV, 1958
  - Bot Ba Njock, Henri Marcel. "Preeminences sociales et systeme politico-religieux dans la societe traditionnelle Bulu et Fang (Social Preeminence and the Political-Religious System in the Traditional Society of the Bulu and Fang)," Journal de la Societe des Africanistes, 1961
    Offprint.
  - Buell, Raymond Leslie. The Native Problem in Africa, 1928
    Photocopy of selected pages.
  - Chilver, E. M. "Nineteenth Century Trade in the Bamenda Grass-fields, Southern Camerouns," Afrika und Ubersee, XLV, 1961
  - Chilver, E. M. and P. M. Kaberry
    - "From Tribute to Tax in a Tikar Chiefdom," Africa, XXX, 1960
      Photoprint.
    - "Traditional Government in Bafut, West Cameroun," The Nigerian Field, XXVIII, undated
  - Dark, Philip. "Notes on the Eton of the Southern French Cameroons," Man, LV, 1955
  - Dominik, Hans (Box 14)
    - Vom Atantik zum Tschadsee: Kriegs-und Forschungs-fahrten in Kamerun (From the Atlantic to Lake Chad: Voyages of War and Discovery in Cameroun), 1908
      Photoprint of selected pages with French translation.
    - Kamerun: sechs Kriegs-und Friendensjahre in den deutschen Tropen (Cameroun: Six Years of War and Peace in the German Tropics), 1901
      Photoprint of selected pages with English translation.
  - Dankelmann (ed.). Mittheilungen von Forschungsreisenden und Gelehrten aus den Deutschen Schutzgebieten (Information from Explorers and Scholars in the German Protectorates), 1889-1890
  - Dussercle, Roger. Du Kilima-Ndjaro au Cameroun: Monseigneur F.-X. Vogt (1870-1943) (From Kilimanjaro to the Cameroun: Monseigneur F.-X. Vogt [1870-1943]), 1950
    Photoprint of selected pages.
  - Franqueville, A. "Naissance et analyse d'un paysage urbain: Yaounde (Birth and Analysis of an Urban Landscape: Yaounde),", 1967
  - Haberer. D. "Jaunde (The Ewondo)," Kamerun, undated
  - Heepe, M. (ed.). "Jaunde-Texte von Karl Atangana und Paul Messi (Ewondo Texts of Charles Atangana and Paul Messi)" in Abhandlungen des Hamburgischen Kolonialinstituts (Transactions of the Hamburg Colonial Institute), 1919
    Photoprint in German and Ewondo; manuscript and typescript with carbon copies of French translation.
  - Institute Geographique National (Yaounde) Service Geographique (Brazzaville). Map of Yaounde, Republique du Cameroun, 1960 (Box 15)
  - Kaberry, Phyllis M.
    - "Retainers and Royal Households in the Cameroons Grassfields," Cahiers d'Etudes Africaines, 10, 196?
    - "Traditional Politics in Nsaw," Africa, XXIX, 1959
  - Kaberry, P. M. and E. M. Chilver. "An Outline of the Traditional Political System of Bali-Nyonga, Southern Cameroons," Africa, XXXI, 1961
  - Morgan, C. Durch Kamerun von Sud nach Nord. Reisen und Forschungen im Hinterlande 1889 bis 1891 (Across the Cameroun from South to North. Travels and Studies in the Interior from 1889 to 1891), 1893
    Photoprint of selected pages; typescript French translation.
  - Nekes, Hermann
    - "Jaunde und seine Bewohner (Sudkamerun) (Yaounde and Its Inhabitants [Southern Cameroun])," Koloniale Rundschau, 8, 1912
      Photoprint with English translation.
    - "Totemistische manistische Anschauungen der Jaunde in ihren Kultfeiern und Geheimbunden (Some Views about Death-Worship and Totemic Symbols in Ewondo Cult Rites and Secret Societies)," Koloniale Rundschau, 9, 1913
      Photoprint with French and English resumes.
    - Vier Jahre im Kameruner Hinterland (Four Years in the Cameroun Hinterland), 1912
  - Passarge, S. "Die Geschichte der Erforschung und Eroberung Kameruns (History of the Exploration and Conquest of the Cameroun)," Beitschrift fur Kolonialpolitik, Kolonialrecht und Kolonialwirtschaft (Note on Colonial Policy, Colonial Law, and Colonial Economy) edited by the Deutschen Kolonialgesellschaft (German Colonial Society), 1908
    Photoprint with French translation.
  - Pogge von Strandmann, H. "The German Role in Africa and German Imperialism: A Review Article," African Affairs, 69, 1970
  - "Die politische Organisation der Eingeborenen und ihre Verwendung fur Verwaltung und Rechtsprechung im Schutzgebiet Kamerun (The Political Organization of the Natives and Its Use for General Administration and the Administration of Justice in the Cameroun Protectorate)," Amtsblatt fur das Schutzgebiet Kameroun (Official Gazette for the Cameroun Protectorate), 1910
  - Puttkamer, Jesko von. Gouverneursjahre in Kamerun (The Governor's Years in the Cameroun), 1912